...che ha da raccontare a noi, e in grado del fatto che il titolo del suo libro sul programma sia in italiano, il suo libro sarà deliverato in inglese.
E lo ringraziamo per questo. Grazie molto.
Come vedete, il più lungo il CV, il più vecchio siete. Questo è piuttosto triste.
Se avessi voluto un CV più lungo e con più o meno oltre i miei occhi.
Il mio tema ha a fare con, diciamo, la relazione tra la democrazia e la performance della democrazia,
i prodotti che aspettiamo dalla democrazia in relazione ai sistemi di governamento che le democrazie tendono ad adottare.
Quelli che sono, basicamente, il regime precedente, il sistema parlamentare, connessi a diversi sistemi electorali.
Penso che molte di voi ricordano che anni fa, scrivendo su la democrazia, questo era il titolo del suo libro all'epoca,
il tuo libro, il libro di Robert Dahl, era nel 1998, ha scritto che sostanzialmente
la maggior parte dei sistemi di governamento potrebbero funzionare in effetti,
in quanto a quelli che si chiamano condizioni strutturali della democrazia, esistono in quel contexto.
E ha riferito, e avrò di nuovo questo in un minuto, principalmente a condizioni che hanno a fare
con la coesione della società, con il sistema economico e altre qualifiche,
qualifiche preliminari per la democrazia, per avere la piattaforma appropiata.
Questo è, prima di tutto, importante per due ragioni.
La prima ragione è che chi è occupato con l'ingegneria costituzionale,
deve essere consapevole che l'ingegneria costituzionale non è solo disegnare
i dispositivi costituzionali, ma ha a più a do con la connessione tra questi dispositivi
e il contesto, come li chiamiamo, a causa di cui questa posizione corretta di Bob Dahl
è anche una sorta di caviata contro la facilità di trasplantare i sistemi di governamento
dal un paese all'altro, che è inoltre ignorata, voglio dire, la caviata.
Quindi, quando c'è, e nel mio paese, qui in Italia, è stata molto frequente,
una demanda per la riforma del sistema di governamento,
hai debiti che, molto facilmente e leggermente,
dicono, dovremmo adottare il francese, o il germano, o l'americano,
come se questi fossero cavi che potessi comprare facilmente,
soltanto che, diciamo, la dimensione sia la dimensione dei tuoi piedi.
Non è così facilmente, non è così facilmente.
Non voglio spendere molto tempo su questo punto,
ma l'appello che ha il sistema francese di governamento in questo paese
tende ad ignorare che questo tipo di sistema sia inconcevibile
senza la tradizione imperiale della Francia,
i due Napoleoni, uno dopo l'altro,
e senza figure esternate,
come l'obiettivo in quel momento speciale della vita francese.
In simile modo,
avere un'elezione elettorale,
scusate, un'elezione diretta
dai cittadini di un Presidente della Repubblica
senza fare a questo Presidente
una figura politica influente
nel sistema di governamento,
può essere fatto in Austria,
per ragioni che non capisco esattamente,
ma bisogna essere un stabilizzatore in Austria
di implicazioni che sarebbero naturali in altri paesi.
Mi ricordo che ho chiesto ai miei amici austriani
come fare una campagna elettorale
rimanendo fuori dalla politica.
Sì, possono farlo,
ma il mio consiglio è,
non provare a farlo così facilmente,
perché potreste essere dissaposti,
inoltre.
Ora,
quelli di noi che sono famosi con la legge costituzionale comparativa
sono perfettamente abituati
alla difficoltà dei trasplantamenti
e ai numerosi problemi
che sono involti in ogni trasplantamento,
che, ancora di nuovo,
applica anche ai sistemi costituzionali.
Lasciando questo qui,
ma potrebbe diventare utile dopo,
mi concentreremo per un secondo
sulle condizioni strutturali
che Dahl
ha listato
nel 1998,
perché
sono i prequisiti
per una democrazia
in paesi che sono iniziali
nella vita democratica.
Quindi,
a un lato,
città indipendenti,
a l'altro lato,
città che passano da un regime autoritario
a una democrazia,
perché ciò che Dahl
indica, prima di tutto,
è il controllo dell'armi
e della polizia
dai politici elettori.
Per te,
per la maggior parte di te,
per quelli di te che vivono in, diciamo,
sistemi democratici a lungo inizio,
questo sembra abbastanza ovvio.
Non aspettate che l'armi e la polizia
non siano sotto controllo
dei politici elettori,
ma potrebbe essere un'issue
nelle democrazie iniziali.
E era, fino a pochi anni fa,
un'issue in Turchia.
Nonostante il fatto
che la secularizzazione arrivò in Turchia
a causa dei militari e dei camalisti,
è un fatto che,
quando stavamo rilasciando
il processo di accessione
di Turchia già anni fa,
una delle ragioni principali,
ricordo ancora il commissione
per l'enlargimento,
dicendo a l'interlocutore turco,
che se le loro instituzioni civili
fossero sotto controllo
dei militari,
non entrerebbero in Unione Europea,
perché questo è un principio
principale per una democrazia.
Ma ancora una volta,
questo era una sorta di caso eccezionale
in un paese europeo come Turchia.
La seconda ragione
era, diciamo,
non avere interventi esterni
e questo tipicamente
si applica ai paesi
che non erano indipendenti
e che stanno diventando indipendenti
mentre si adottano una democrazia.
Un'economia di mercato
con garantie sicure
di diritti di proprietà.
Questa ragione è tipica
di paesi emergenti.
E c'era un'ultima
condizione
che è una sorta di grado,
in mio punto di vista,
tra, diciamo, i necessari
di una democrazia iniziale
e i necessari di una democrazia lunga,
un subculturismo limitato,
un pluralismo, lo lascio
come è in questo momento.
La conclusione di Bob Dole
era che, se le condizioni
del listo esistono,
più o meno tutti i sistemi
del governo possono lavorare
a sicurezza dei prodotti
di democrazia,
di trasparenza, di responsabilità,
di giudizia umana, di giudizia minoritaria,
eccetera, se le condizioni
sono meno che favoribili,
questo erano le sue parole al momento,
fai attenzione, perché ci sono sistemi
che ti disapointano. E sicuramente
si è concentrato sul modello
di presidenza
coppando
l'elezione diretta di un presidente
con un sistema proporzionale
dell'elezione del Parlamento.
E il suo consiglio era
che questo fosse un paese pericoloso,
fai attenzione, e se non hai
tutte le condizioni favoribili,
questo potrebbe
portare a conseguenze
Ma questo è un tipo di
per me, perché il punto
che voglio imparare
sotto la vostra attenzione è un altro.
E è il fatto
che siamo forzati
a capire che anche
le democrazie lunghe e mature
hanno le loro
condizioni strutturali,
che, come ho detto all'inizio,
tendiamo a prendere per granted, ma che
non necessariamente sono granted
e potrebbero, diciamo,
essere erogati da dentro.
Un po' di giorni fa
stavo debattendo con i filosoferi,
quindi ero l'unico non filosofero
del panel.
L'issue usuale del
diciamo,
l'etnicità e la religione, le diversità
vivendo insieme nel stesso paese,
i loro rolli, i loro dialoghi,
i loro misunderstandi, i loro conflitti,
eccetera. E il filosofero
come Charles Taylor,
che è, diciamo, open-minded
come pochi altri
intellettuali che abbiamo nel nostro
paese occidentali,
era molto preoccupato
con il destino della democrazia,
ha detto,
perché, ripeto le sue parole,
la democrazia necessita
una solidarietà basica,
una coesione fondamentale,
e questa solidarietà basica,
questa coesione fondamentale,
è, in qualche modo,
a rischio
in diversi paesi nostri,
a causa di alcune ragioni che
avrò a dire immediatamente,
e come funzioneranno le nostre democrazie
se queste
indipendenti,
necessitano, in qualche modo,
diventare, diciamo,
sottile o sottile.
Quando
mi spieghe ai miei studenti
il senso dell'Unione Europea,
che definisco
un hermaphrodite,
che è, diciamo, in-between
sistemi internazionali
e sistemi di governamento
costituzionale,
uno dei problemi cruciali è
perché ci sono paesi
in cui tutti noi,
e riferisco agli Stati membri dell'Unione Europea,
accettano la maggior parte del voto,
mentre ci sono altri paesi
in cui vogliamo l'unanimità
come sistema di voto.
Bene, chiaramente potete trovare
alcune esplanazioni,
ma il punto principale è che
dove noi accettiamo
la maggior parte del voto,
significa che la distanza
tra noi è più lunga
e, per questo, diciamo,
la distanza tra noi
è abbastanza
per permetterci di accettare
la maggior parte del voto
che potrebbe escludere il nostro paese.
Mentre ci sia l'unanimità,
significa che la distanza tra noi
non è abbastanza
e, per questo, vogliamo
avere un veto
su quella decisione
che non può essere presa contro me.
Ora, considerate che
ogni sistema democratizzato
è basato sulla maggior parte del voto,
indipendentemente del sistema elettorale,
ovviamente, ma il senso della democrazia
è che c'è una comunità
che, all'interno della comunità,
la distanza è così che
ogni decisione può essere adottata
dalla maggior parte del voto
e non mai l'unanimità
è considerata necessaria
perché c'è sufficiente confusione mutua.
Non condivido quella opzione
del mio oponente politico,
ma è parte del range
delle opzioni che considero
accettabile per il presente e il futuro del mio paese
e, domani, lo potrei corregire
se necessario.
Ma questo è il senso basato
di, diciamo,
essere insieme
in una comunità runta da una democrazia.
Un sistema autoritario
ignora questo tipo di prequisito.
Potrebbe pagare il prezzo per l'ignorazione,
ma ignora questo prequisito.
La decisione è presa
perché c'è sufficiente, diciamo,
per l'instituzione o qualsiasi cosa,
per l'implementare. Non chiedo
gli altri. Ora,
cosa sta succedendo
nella nostra società oggi,
nella società che sono sempre, sempre
nella nostra, diciamo, memoria
runta dal sistema democrazioso?
Beh, quel subculturale
limitato del pluralismo
è diventato meno e meno limitato.
È aumentato
in modo che
questo è più tipico
dell'Europa che dell'U.S.
L'U.S. è un'altra storia,
ma certamente considero questo fatto molto semplice
che,
poiché il Dio Almighty
ha inventato il Stato della nazione
alcuni secoli,
in i nostri paesi continentali
qualsiasi cosa diciamo
per la città, la città
è stata basata sull'identità nazionale.
Ci sono paesi che daranno più ruolo
all'uso solido
e altri all'uso sanguinista,
ma, basicamente, Francia,
Germania, Italia, Spagna
e altri paesi polandici
con la stessa
raccolta culturale,
più o meno la stessa religione,
la stessa colore della pelle.
Ora abbiamo milioni
e milioni di persone
che entrano nelle nostre comunità,
che diventano cittadini,
che dovrebbero diventare cittadini
perché si setturano qui.
A questo punto la città non è basata
sull'identità nazionale,
è basata su altre ragioni.
Potrebbe essere che,
a causa di queste altre ragioni,
ci sono distanze che rimane
e che rimane
in background
una sorta di intoleranza per l'altro
che potrebbe esplodere in ogni momento.
Ma la seconda ragione
che in alcuni paesi
somehow aggiunge alla prima,
in alcuni altri,
è lavorare sopra di loro.
Nel caso dell'U.S. è uno degli esempi.
La seconda ragione
è la profonda cambiata
nella relazione tra i cittadini
e gli actori politici,
dove non c'è più intermedia
nel termine, diciamo,
delle strutture sociali,
dei partiti, delle unioni,
che, in qualche modo,
possono permettere
i due poli di questa relazione
di discutere con l'altro,
di capire l'altro
e di modificare le loro posizioni iniziali.
Ora c'è il leadership
che parla ai cittadini
durante la media, principalmente,
che lead a tre conseguenze.
La seconda ragione è la simplificazione
del messaggio politico,
la radicalizzazione del messaggio politico,
perché per essere più semplice
significa essere più radicale,
la distorsione dei argomenti
su cui la scelta potrebbe essere adattata.
Ti ricordi Giovanni Sartori
e la dilemma
tra la videocracia, come l'ha chiamata,
e la democrazia?
Ora, puoi dire che ora c'è Internet,
le persone vengono online, ecc.
Non cambia.
Non cambia questo punto di base.
Ora, questo è un cambiamento enormesimo,
perché hai
la...
Take the example of the campaign
against the health reform of President Obama.
There were false arguments
creating terror
among the elderly.
They will unplug you to save money.
There won't be any more money
to cure you.
It was false, completely false,
but several citizens
were somehow oriented
on the basis of these arguments.
The reactions
tend to be equally simplified
and again radicalized.
Now, a political debate
that is both simplified
and radicalized
is a debate that
somehow opens up
societies,
creates cleavages
difficult to remedy
and changes the sense
of institutions.
Democracy means
that the demos
should take the basic decisions.
In this kind of system
there is a sort of pollution
of the demos.
When I saw the
BP oil
in the Mexico Gulf,
it came to my mind at this point
that those waters
are exactly the same
as the waters of a democracy
where all of these polluting
ingredients enter
and form the opinions.
The transformation
of the US is impressive.
We all loved in the past
the figure of the US President
as it was explained
by constitutional experience
and by American scholars.
We have a wide country
fragmented into several
member states,
fragmented because you can become
an American coming from anywhere
in the world.
This wonderful, beautiful thing
that national identity came after
not before, it's not a prerequisite
but it's where you go.
You become an American
and of course in order for this to happen
you need a unifying figure
at the top of the system.
The President of the United States
is the unifying figure of the country.
All these elements
or this variety
of sources of Americanhood
are somehow connected
by making the choice
of a President who will be
either a Democrat or a Republican
but he or she
one day will happen
is or will be the President
of all the Americans.
Now this is exactly what President Obama
had in mind and he wanted
to restore after the years
very much controversial of George W
the American presidency
as the unifying institution
of the country. It turned out impossible
and not due to him
but due to the fact that the unifying role
of the President was rejected
and the country is somehow
moved by extreme positions
more and more
and all of us are looking
at the Tea Parties
as an increasing force
that might have an impact
on the Republicans I hope
less than now
we might be fearful of
but it is a fact
that losing that
60th Senator was like
losing an important battle
because it became obvious
that filibustering could not be
fought against
as it was considered necessary.
I can tell you that
this change
in the US
but also in all of our
countries
is the reason due to which I changed my mind.
Leonardo Morlino wanted me to
explain to you today why I was in favor
of a presidential regime in Italy
15 years ago
while now I speak against it.
Well the reason is precisely this one
because I thought
that for my country
this kind of miracle
the miracle of a working democracy
you elect the President
on a majoritarian basis
and the President becomes
the unifying figure of the country
so it's the miracle of a democracy
now the miracle is gone
and I'm sure
that in a country like Italy
where we succeeded somehow
in defusing
the let's say
sharp divide between
liberal democratic parties and the communist party
because after
years and years
on coexistence
under the democratic rules
of a democratic constitution somehow
it was defused.
Incredibly enough after the end of communism
we have a renewed
polarization that is even sharper
and harsher
than it was at the time
of a communist regime
linked to the Soviet Union
in terms of implications
on our domestic arena
so it's astonishing but that's the way it is.
So imagining
that imagine
that the let's say
Prime Minister of Italy of today
becoming President
of the Republic
elected by the people which could happen
had we the direct
election of the President quite likely
the current Prime Minister
could be elected President of the Republic
would he represent the entire nation
would he be perceived as the representative
of all Italians or
he would make even more
even deeper the cleavage
that is already dividing dangerously
the Italians.
So being things
in these terms
what's that?
Because the computer is on
you're right.
Okay I leave it as it is.
Being things as they are
the main
question in
shaping or reshaping
a system of government
is the following
the system I'm going to adopt
will it
amplify
or bridge
the let's say
polarization
that tends to exist
should I act
aiming at bridging
or aiming at amplifying?
I let's say
ask you this
I'm not thinking I want to be clear
of consortium democracy as the best solution
not at all
not at all because let's say by instinct
for a politologist the answer could be
well if you want to bridge
the main bridge is the
consortium democracy. No.
Consortium democracy is an exceptional
kind of system of government
that makes sense under exceptional
conditions but when I refer
to bridging I'm not referring
to a system due to which there is
no majority and no opposition
but to a system where majority
and opposition share
a common platform.
We tend to say of values of principles etc.
these are vague notions
but they are let's say
there is enough to accept
as the majority rule without
resenting it as a sort of
undue imposition
upon me.
So making a system
where
majority and opposition may
offer their options
to the citizens and the distance
between the options is not disruptive.
Let's say you
in this country
you cannot build
your mosques full stop.
If you want to build
mosques in this country
you have to accept my church
in Islamic countries.
It's difficult sometimes for me
to let's say
promote the argument
according to which should
a democracy adopt the reciprocity
principle it could never exist.
Quite obviously
because you always find a country
that is not democratic
that goes beyond the boundaries
of reciprocity. So that country
cannot become the benchmark
of a democratic system because it's not
a democratic benchmark.
But this kind of conflict might arise.
At that point you see
and I go toward my
confused conclusion because
it's easier for me to
analyze a difficulty
than to find the answer
to remove the difficulty itself.
There is something
that I would call reinventing democracy
that goes beyond
adopting a presidential or a
parliamentary system. This is really a
minor aspect of the problem
that we are facing. We are facing
the same kind of problem that
President Obama is now tackling
with the Mexico Gulf waters.
So revitalizing
the demos of our
societies, recreating
therefore a platform of mutual
understanding and
preventing
that kind of political
maneuvering that
is built upon amplifying
conflicts.
Because something we have to be aware of
is that conflicts do exist in society
but frequently
it is a responsibility of the
political elite
bridging or amplifying.
You may decide that the easiest
way to more votes
for you is amplifying and you
amplify.
And in several European
countries becoming
xenophobic is the cheapest
let's say
way to
gain votes from
at least a part of your electorate.
So this is where
we have to reinvent
something.
I would say that first
I tend to prefer a parliamentary system
because
unless you have the
exceptional case of the states
and now I forget what I have said
up to now I only think of the institutions
which is not presidential.
It's presidential
congressional
and the role of congress
should be taken on board.
You can't have
even a transplant of that system
if you only adopt the presidency.
You also have to have a very strong
parliament such as the congress is.
But this is something not easy to have.
It is a fact that historically only in the US
an elected president is balanced
by such a strong
congress. Nowhere else this happens.
There has to be a reason.
I tend to prefer parliamentary systems.
I think that a very
delicate arena
for reform has to do with standing
orders of parliaments
finding a sort of third way
between filibustering on the one side
and
deciding whatever
by votes of confidence
without allowing the parliament
that kind of procedural life
that is important.
Perhaps only legal scholars
can duly appreciate
the substantive value
of some procedures.
But there are some procedures in parliament
due to which
members of parliament of different
and even opposing parties
somehow take part
in the same kind of game.
And at the end even though the decision
is of the majority
the opposition members of parliament
recognize part of their own
imprint in the final decisions.
It was an important moment
when in this country that was after all
the beginning
after World War II
the decisions adopted
by the majority
were named decisions of parliament
and not decisions of
the Christian democrats. So it had
a meaning. The procedure had
produced something.
And this is something
that can be done.
Second the electoral system is crucial.
Bob Dole was right.
There is a connection between institutions
and the systems that you adopt
to elect them. So making
the members of parliament
as responsible as possible
towards their electors.
This is absolutely fundamental.
They should be responsible to their
electors, not to the leaders.
Otherwise there is no
interplay between
the parliament and the executive.
There are electoral systems
that make the individual members
of parliament responsible to the leaders.
There are systems that make them responsible
to the electors. Systems
due to which a parliamentarian
can say to his
prime minister, I can't vote this.
My electors would not accept it.
Not in all
of our systems members of parliament
have this kind of, let's say,
need because it becomes
for them a need.
And the final part,
even more important I would say,
and I throw it here
because I really have the demand
only, how can we make
deliberative democracy
something that goes beyond
the expensive experiments of James
Fishkin?
Because a democracy cannot be
such if it's not deliberative.
And that system of simplified
and radicalized messages
completely destroys
the deliberative segment
of the relationship between
political leaderships and citizens.
Now we have all the necessary
means. We have these technologies.
We can talk to each other easily.
We can interact easily.
Can we imagine using
several systems due to which, let's say,
political parties themselves
consider their own internal
life something that has to
occur throughout
experiments of deliberative
democracies? This is what I said for instance
to the Italian Democratic Party.
If you want to have a role toward
your, let's say, members in the
country, you have to somehow
involve them into this kind
of exercise. Don't leave it
to scholarly experiences
because you have the means and you have
the opportunity. You know how to gather
the people and let them discuss.
Let them be aware of the reasons
that are behind a possible decision
of an option. There is an
enormous value added
in this kind of relationships
in terms of equalizing people
with each other.
Because the voice of any of us
has the same weight around
that kind of huge table than the voice
of anybody else. The topics
exist. And we know that the topics
are ignored when
the message only arrives
with the opinion. And therefore
the citizens feel the humiliation
of becoming
fans of this team or of
that other team without having the
opportunity of doing
what has to be done.
I close by noticing
I am a great admirer of Bob Dole
also because, I mean, he has been writing
so many things for so many years.
It's changing his opinions. I like this
thing that
a new book and a new opinion. I don't like
it anymore as I have done with the
presidential system. But it's not for that
reason. In eight years
later, when he wrote
on political equality, he
listed again the structural
conditions for a democratic
system to work.
And eight years later
these conditions were different
from those that he had listed in
1998. And you can understand
after my, let's say,
arguments of a minute ago
that he had exactly the same
let's say, issues in mind.
He says that
the minimum for a democracy
is actual participation
of people,
fair information,
items on the agenda
decided by the people.
So you might think, but this is obvious.
It's not obvious at all.
It's exactly what we are losing,
what we are destroying.
And reinventing democracy
is not reinventing